This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions about software
engineering topics at least once a
month. Thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the podcast.
Hello, this is Scott Chelius. I am here
with Steve Will, who is the chief
architect of the IBM i, traditionally
known as OS/400. Good morning, how are
you, Steve?
I'm doing very well today, thank you
very much.
Thank you very much for joining me
today. Well, why don't we begin? Maybe
you can just introduce yourself, your
role at IBM.
I am the chief architect for IBM i, and
we'll talk quite a bit about what IBM i
is. It's an IBM operating system, and
chief architect, in my role, I'm
responsible for the strategy for this
operating system, and the plan. So, I'm
involved in setting
what we're going to be spending our
money on, how our developers are going
to be spending their time, looking out
into
three-to-five-year time frame for what
customers are going to need and what the
industry is going to be presenting.
I've been at IBM for 26 years now.
I work in the Rochester, Minnesota lab.
I came here directly out of college and
then
out of graduate school. I graduated with
a degree in
computer science and mathematics from
Luther College in Decorah, Iowa, and
then I got my master's degree in
computer science at Purdue University.
So, IBM has been where I've spent my
career, and I have essentially spent my
career on this platform and its
predecessors.
Why don't we just dive right into the
platform itself? Won't you briefly
describe for us IBM i and introduce us
to it?
Okay.
Well, IBM i is an operating system
that's used by hundreds of thousands of
businesses throughout the world. Uh it
got its start its architecture was
initially created at its lowest level
with the System 38 back in the 1970s
and then grew into uh the AS/400 which
maybe many of your listeners would have
heard of.
But over time uh the AS/400 which had
its own proprietary software uh
grew up and merged in its technologies
its underlying hardware and IO
technologies with other systems within
IBM and so now IBM i is the integrated
operating system. That's what I stands
for is integration. The integrated
operating system that sits on top of our
systems.
Tell us a little bit about why why I why
why IBM i what's what is different about
this platform than so many other
platforms and why is it not generally
heard nearly as much as say uh a Windows
or a Linux?
Okay.
So
I is
from its architecture um
very business oriented. When the
architecture was put together initially
the idea was that businesses want to run
their businesses and not their
computers.
And
our architects knew that we had to put
together an integrated platform that
would be exceptionally easy to use. And
so they de-
decided from the very beginning to
create an operating system that was
going to be object-based so it'd be very
difficult to do anything wrong
that it was going to have integrated
database that had a lot of automated
features that other platforms would
require a database administrator
professional to to do operations instead
have the system do those operations for
them. Built on several architectural
concepts including something called
single level store and then our multiple
workload management system which is a
subsystem based system that allows
customers to essentially forget about
many of the management technology
management experiences and requirements
that are on other platforms. So, we
really are from an architectural view
significantly different and we can talk
about that of course later. But one of
the reasons that you don't hear much
about us is that we got sold into the
small and medium business markets
in the United States, in Europe, in
fact, around the world in the '90s and
those folks who bought us, they're not
out there trying to uh
talk about what technology they have and
in general they don't even really care.
They care about the business that they
have. And as those businesses grew into
some of the largest businesses into the
world in the world, they also adopted
other technologies around them and so
they don't go out and trumpet that
they're running i but in fact so many of
the businesses that you deal with on a
day-to-day basis are actually using IBM
i and they're using it very successfully
and have been for years. I
have uh a number of different specific
examples of clients who are using the
platform. Um sometimes I have to get
special permission but let me just give
you an idea. If you live uh in Europe or
you live in the United States and you
call your cable company and you want to
get some service from them or upgrade or
whatever, um the people you're talking
to on the other end are probably using
IBM i. Um, if you're in the US and you
live in a country in a community that's
under a hundred thousand
people, um,
and you go and work with your
law enforcement agency or your,
uh,
county government or your city
government, you're probably dealing with
people who are using IBM i because those
companies or those institutions
bought our platform because they have
specific applications that run their
institution or their business really
well and as they grew up, they just
continued to use it because it continued
to work.
So, going back to the history
Mhm.
of IBM i and you you talked a little bit
about System 38 and AS/400. Can you give
us just a little bit of timeline, uh,
you know, where did IBM i start? What
was the original reason for the
introduction of the IBM i and then work
us from the System 38 down to the AS/400
and then I believe and you can help
clarify this for our listeners that, uh,
at one point the AS/400, which I think
you'll talk about, actually had its own
hardware but now has a consolidated, uh,
IBM hardware, yes?
Sure. Yes, that's exactly true. Um, so,
in the 70s, the System 38 was created.
It was, uh, meant to be a business
computer for mid-size companies, maybe
small companies and the core
architecture of IBM i came from there,
although it added some architectural
layers over time. Um, we can talk about
those as well, but that was introduced
in 1977, 1978. At about the same time,
there was another IBM mid-range system.
Uh, at the time we were called
microcomputers. I don't know if anybody
even remembers that phrase, but there
was the System 38 that I talked about
and then there was a System 36.
The System 36 was really focused on ease
of use. When I talk about people like
dentists' offices and sheriffs' offices
picking up this platform, in fact, most
of them initially bought the System 36
because it was by far the easiest system
to manage.
The System 38 had a lot of great
underlying
architecture that helped the platform be
long-lived and very, very stable.
So, in the late '70s and early '80s, IBM
had these two platforms, System 36 and
System 38. And they decided that they
wanted to take the ease of use from the
System 36,
but underlie it with this architecture
uh
and the architectural elements from the
System 38. And from that
came the AS/400.
And the AS/400 was initially introduced
in 1988 as a
consolidation of those two
architectures.
It became
the most popular small medium business
platform ever. Um and then over time, it
became clear that while we were
developing our own specific hardware for
AS/400, and that included then
developing all of the associated
specific
IO devices and communication
capabilities,
that IBM would be a far better off
financially if we
could converge that hardware and IO
investment with the other platforms. At
the same time, we had our Unix platform,
which at that point was called the
RS/6000. And it was off competing in the
Unix marketplace, but it was also doing
its own specific uh
hardware. So, way back in uh 1998, we
began our journey down a converged road
map, where the processors that we were
going to all build on were the initial
power processors.
Now, all of us, all of our operating
systems in this line, are sitting on top
of the power processor. We use all
common IO, and in fact, much of the IO
that we attach today is actually out
there in the industry for other people
to attach.
We attach common disks that are
available to everybody else, and so on.
Whereas in the past, we had to produce
our own disks and so on, and that
required a lot more investment. So, now
we can focus our investment for IBM i.
IBM i is just the name of the operating
system now that sits on top of our
systems that carries forward that
architecture and that value that came
out of the AS/400. And we can just focus
our
investment on keeping that platform
doing what it does really, really well,
while we run on top of the power
architecture. By the way, the power
architecture is very widely used
in in the world today. It's not just
running AIX or Unix, it's not just
running Linux on power, and it's not
just running IBM i, but there are power
chips inside of all of the major gaming
consoles. So, PS3, a Nintendo Wii,
they're using power chips. They just
happen to be slightly different modified
so that they can run games really fast
as opposed to running businesses really
fast.
Now, let's get to a few things you
discussed a little bit earlier. You were
discussing IBM i
as an object-oriented
operating system. And what does that
mean?
Okay. Well, we actually talk about it as
being object-based instead of
object-oriented, and and I'll tell you a
little bit about why. If software
engineers listening to this will
understand that
an object-oriented language has certain
uh implications when you talk about it.
It It means that there are going to
objects, and those objects can only be
operated upon by certain methods. That's
what we usually talk about. Well,
it also tends to mean uh in the
strictest definition that an
object-oriented language allows you to
do inheritance, to be able to create
another object type inheriting
capabilities. There is no inheritance in
IBM i, and so we don't specifically call
it object-oriented, but we do call it
object-based because
the the step right before
object-oriented is object-based. In
other words, that part of what makes
things an object that allows you to only
operate on the object using specific
operations specific to that object. And
this has been really key for us to be
able to have
the kind of integrity and security that
we have in the operating system. Now,
this is different than what people are
used to with the other operating systems
that are most popularly known. And so,
let me try to explain.
If you have a text file on IBM i, you
can edit it and delete it, but you can't
try to run it. You can't even change its
name to change its say extension to look
like a program and then run it. If it
was a text object, it's a text object,
and it can't be run. On the other side,
if you have a program, there's no way
you can go in and edit it. You can't
change its name and then operate on it
as an editor. It is a program object,
and you can only do certain things
there. So, having that object-based
platform allows us to ensure that each
of the objects is only going to do or be
operated on uh by its intended
operations. And this actually makes it
very robust. Uh things can't
accidentally do things uh to objects
that they're not supposed to do. Uh
We have built our security all based on
roles and objects. So, a role in the
system might be, for example, like I'm a
programmer. All right, if you have the
programmer role, you can operate on a
program by being able to recreate that
program using a compiler.
But, if you're just an ordinary user,
you can't. And that's all based on role
plus object. So, I as a programmer might
be able to use my compiler to change a
line change a program in one area, but
because I'm not authorized to another
object, I might not be able to do that.
And so, this object- based technology
that we have really helps in our
integrity, in our reliability, and in
our security.
Okay. So, in Unix, everything is a file
for
most part. And you have
obviously have ACLs with group and user
permissions and and things like that. Is
that roughly similar? Or, you know, how
different is it from a for instance a a
Unix security model?
Okay. Um
it's
over time, the Unix security model and
the i model have gotten closer to one
another. And let me just make clear, we
have the capability to have
we have a Unix-like file system on the
platform that can be used by programs,
for example, Java programs that need to
have that sort of directory structure
and that sort of security model. But, in
each of those cases where we have that,
we are still protected by our
object-based and role-based security
model.
Whereas, in the pure file system that
initially came out of out of the AS/400
heritage, an object is not just a file.
An object has a specific type. So, if
you have a message queue, it's not a
file with messages in it. It is an
object called a message queue, which can
have attached to it objects that are
message objects, and they can be
operated upon by reading from the
message queue, putting something on the
message queue, but they aren't just
files that can be read and written. You
use specific APIs, application
programming interfaces, to make those
operations happen.
Yet, in the file system that looks more
like a Unix file system, you can do all
the normal F opens, F closes, writes,
and reads, that sort of thing. You're
still going through the object-based
security model because even in that
Unix-like file system, you're running
under a user profile, and you are
operating upon that thing, even though
you're using an F open, F close, a read,
write.
You have to have authority to that file
object, just as you would on a Unix-type
system. It's just It's based on our user
profile as opposed to the kind of Unix
users that are out there.
So, it sounds like it's even the
services themselves are exposed as
objects from the system.
That is true. That is true.
One other thing that you said, which I
find fascinating here, is a single-level
store.
Mhm.
This is probably, you know, getting down
into the into the weeds here of the
platform, but I think this is probably
sets apart IBM i from most other
operating systems, and and possibly has
impact on the programming model. Can you
describe what the single-level store is?
Sure.
Single-level store is a key concept
because it is one of the architectures
that defines how we do everything we do
at the lowest levels of the operating
system, and yet programmers often don't
need to be aware of it.
Single-level store,
let me give you kind of a an analogy
that a programmer would understand.
Single level store treats every bit of
storage that's attached to IBM i as if
it were memory starting at byte zero and
going all the way up to 16 bytes worth
of addressable storage. Okay. So, from a
programmer's point of view
you don't have to um worry about whether
you're going to overrun memory because
memory is storage.
And you just said 16 bytes. Is that 128
bits?
Yep.
Okay, so that that's really a 128-bit
address space.
That's that's correct. Yeah, so every
every program, even if you're writing in
a language that only has um
a a pointer that's a 4-byte pointer
under the covers we are treating all of
our storage as if it were this long long
string of memory.
Okay. And because of that we don't force
where things are on disk because we need
to know at the lowest levels of the
operating system, we need to know where
every bit of memory, which is really
storage, where it is so that we can
balance things under the covers to
perform as well as possible.
So, in other operating systems we tend
to um force administrators or
programmers to know specifically
on which volume or which disk things are
stored. That is not the case in IBM i.
In IBM i that's taken care of by our
integrated storage management. It's all
based on this single level store.
Again, it doesn't get exposed
necessarily to a customer who's writing
an application except that it simplifies
things because he doesn't need to know
or or try to manage um in which set of
storage is his file located or is his
program located? And we have a lot of
algorithms under the covers to make sure
that the data that is most frequently
being read and written is in the best
possible storage locations.
And so, for example, when we introduced
solid state drives here 2 years ago,
solid state drives are much much faster
than spinning drives, not quite as fast
as memory, but you know, pretty fast.
Well, because our single-level store
and our integrated storage management
know that those solid state drives are
out there and that they're much faster,
we can balance and put data there if a
customer is, for example, reading a lot
of their customer data at the end of the
month, um we can make sure that that
data migrates onto those solid state
drives. And again, the customer didn't
need to worry about that. The
application certainly didn't need to
change, and we were able to take
advantage of that because under the
covers with single-level store, we're
having to do all of that management.
The address space itself is, you know, I
guess the only way I could put an
analogy to it is, you know, I take a
look at uh a file system and I've got a
certain level of storage and and some of
that is is set aside as swap or
something. Is single-level store like a
memory map, like a big memory map file,
or how does it eventually become durable
then?
Okay. Yeah, it is it's it's similar to a
memory map. You can think about that
again at the lowest level of IBM i's
operating system,
the storage management components have
to know, based on portions of the
address,
on which piece of storage it should go
look to do the read. So, there is some
mapping done based on uh header
information that's part of the part of
the pointer, um where to go look for
that. But,
when we put something in memory, when
somebody does a write, we are going to
force that thing out onto the disk that
it's associated with. And this is
actually something very similar to what
a lot of operating systems do, right?
You put something in memory and you keep
it there because you know that the
programs have been using it heavily.
But, you send it out to backing store as
soon as it's going to be convenient, as
soon as you have a bunch of stuff to put
out there. So, while I've said that all
of our storage is treated as if it were
one big stream of memory, and that's
absolutely true, a portion of that is
essentially mirrored in in the memory
for the system. And gets forced out when
when it's convenient and it has the
performance to do so. So, we are very
historically reliable. We put the data
out as quickly as we can to to permanent
backing store, but we treat every piece
of backing store as if it were memory so
that we can manage things under the
covers to make things as efficient as
possible in our memory and storage
usage.
Programs and programs themselves are not
explicitly sending things to backing
store. I mean, basically, they're
they're allocating space and should need
to be stored or go to that backing
store, the operating system's doing it
for them.
That's right.
We also have a temporary file system
that people can use if they know that
they're creating data that's never going
to need to go out to backing store. Many
web programs, for example, store things
in files that they never really intend
to put out on backing store. And so, we
have a portion of our file system that
is the temporary file system. But, by
and large, you'll find that most
applications, when they say they want to
write something to disk, they don't care
how to write it to disk. They just say,
"I want to store this information." And
they expect IBM i is going to put it out
there and keep track of it, and that's
what we do.
Sounds very similar to I just read uh
some architectural notes on the project
varnish, and I'm going to forget the the
person who who wrote that, so I won't I
won't attempt his name to
uh just out of respect, but something
very similar saying, you know, it's
programming that so many programs and so
many operating systems are still using
and that we we maintain programs with
the concept of two different areas. We
have a memory area and we have a and we
have a storage or we have a file system
or some other area. And the operations
that we use between them, we're just
doing it in such an old model. You know,
we need to that's not the way that
really operating systems need to be be
looked at. And sounds like IBM taking
care of that for quite some time then.
Yes, that's been our our hallmark um
since the beginning. We knew for a long
time, and it's finally coming into
existence that while spinning disks are
still always going to be used for
certain things, eventually things like
solid state drives would get out there,
and you would want to be able to treat
everything that you're putting on your
system as if it were just part of
memory. And of course, the amount of
memory that's in a system these days is
huge. If people are still trying to
manage memory versus disk separately in
their applications, there is a certain
amount of that that is becoming less and
less necessary because of the speeds at
which data can be referred to both a
disk as well as solid state disk and
memory itself.
I've got a question about uh DB2 that
you discussed.
Uh a little bit earlier you said IBM i
has DB2. Is that embedded or does that
just come with IBM i? What How is DB2
integrated here?
Oh.
This is a great question and another
huge differentiator between us and other
operating systems, so it's a good thing
to talk about.
If you remember what I talked about the
history here of the system 38 and the
System 36.
We knew that every business is going to
use its computers to store data. That's
That's their business. That's their
data.
So, we knew that every application that
was going to be written to run on top of
this was going to need a database.
So, the architecture of the System 38
and then the AS/400 was
we're going to make our machine the
database machine. We're going to embed a
database within it. The operating system
is going to use the database anytime it
needs to store data. The database is
always going to have access to the
lowest levels of the operating system so
it can interact very well with the
single-level store.
So, DB2
on i started out as our own internal
architected integrated
database. Now, over time the DB2 brand
was invented uh in IBM
so that we could uh compete in the
database market. And other DB2s, such as
the ones that are run on Linux, Unix,
and Windows, are sold as separate
products that run on top of operating
systems.
We became DB2 on i when we adopted the
same standards that were being used in
other databases and in particular other
DB2s.
So, you can access our integrated
database using completely standard SQL.
SQL that will run on every other
platform.
And under the covers then that gets
translated into the database operations
on our machine.
I I want to make this clear because most
databases
are actually written as if um they are a
separate layer on top of a file system
such as other people have.
Not so here. We have multiple layers of
our operating system. We can talk about
that in a minute if you want to. There's
an upper level of the operating system
where when you compile a C program, for
example, it gets compiled to use that
upper level of the operating system and
all of the APIs. But, it actually gets
compiled into a kind of intermediate
language that we call the Technology
Independent Machine Interface. And then
below that is a layer of the operating
system that no user program can touch.
It's sort of like a kernel, but there's
a lot more in it than a kernel.
Well, some of those MI TIMI operations
are actually database operations. When
you compile your program and it's got
SQL in it, it's actually compiling to a
set of instructions that are database
instructions. It's going to build an
index. It's going to do a query. In
fact, many of the indexes that get built
are actually built under the covers
without the APIs um being exposed at
all, without the applications needing to
know it. So, our DB2 is actually the
grown-up version of this integrated
database that we put out there
before there was an SQL, before there
were even standards on how to do uh
database operations. And we use it as an
integrated part of managing the system.
So, there is no separating DB2 from the
IBM i operating system. It's inherent to
it. What makes it much like the other
DB2s is the standard interfaces that can
be used. And then what makes it
different from other DB2s, as well as
other databases out there in the
industry, is because we have integrated
this and because it's built on top of
this single-level store architecture,
there's much less database
administration that needs to be done by
a user. Many of the things to make sure
that tables are spread properly across
disks so that we get the right
performance, building indices that are
going to be used commonly often gets
done automatically by our operating
system and by our DB2 as opposed to
having to have a database administrator
figure that all out. So, that's what we
talk about and what we mean when we talk
about DB2 being part of IBM i as opposed
to
sitting on top of it.
Expand a little bit. You said there's
kind of the upper and lower levels and
when you went to the upper levels you
were talking about SQL APIs, making
query, JDBC, and and obtain data back.
But you talked about lower level and you
talked about
Yeah. So, TIMI, sometimes we call it the
MI, sometimes we call it TIMI, T I M I.
Again, it means technology independent
machine interface. We have two layers of
our operating system as I mentioned.
Our operating system at the upper level,
pure IBM i part of it, it gets compiled
to this technology independent machine
interface. And so do applications. They
also get compiled to this technology
independent machine interface.
Again,
several kinds of operations there. The
kinds of operations you would expect to
see, reads and writes and so on, but
they also have these specialized things
for our database.
Now, the reason that we have that TIMI,
that machine independent interface,
is that we knew that over time things
like processor models, IO and so on,
they're going to change. But we didn't
want to have to force customers to
recompile for those changes. So, we were
initially, for example,
a 48-bit machine.
When the AS/400 came out, it was a
48-bit machine.
But our programmers,
the people who write applications on top
of the platform didn't need to worry
about that. They wrote their programs
dealing with pointers and spaces and so
on
in their language, whatever language
they were writing in, RPG, C, whatever.
And it would get compiled down to this
MI.
And those instructions didn't have any
awareness
of what
the capabilities were of the processor
underneath.
So, when we moved from a 48-bit
processor to a 64-bit processor such as
the one we're doing today, the lower
level of the operating system underneath
that machine independent interface,
okay?
That had to change. But, the upper level
of the operating system didn't need to
and furthermore, the applications didn't
need to be recompiled because the
applications were not compiled down to
that 48-bit machine, they were actually
compiled to this intermediate layer. And
then when you would installed your
program or you restored your program
from the 48-bit machine onto the 64-bit
machine, we were able to do all the
retranslation
of those uh
instructions
because you had been compiled to this
intermediate step, we could
automatically do that retranslation to
run on the new hardware. And that has
happened several times as we've moved.
So, we actually have programs that were
written for the System 38 that customers
have out there or for the System 36 that
customers have out there that haven't
been changed or recompiled since 1980,
but they still run on our system because
they were initially compiled to that
technology independent machine interface
and we've been able to carry along that
functionality because we haven't forced
those customers to recompile even as
we've changed underlying IO or
underlying processor technologies.
Okay, that sounds remarkably like a Java
runtime or CLR.net runtime.
That's right. It's It's It's that
concept only applied to everything that
runs on the system including older
languages that were compiled. Java has
that concept and it's it's
totally understandable why you would
want to get to that, right? You don't
want to have to recompile based on um
technology changes.
When the code runs,
there's there's a little bit of a
difference there, I think. You are
saying that it's not just recompile, but
it is compiled into machine code. The
The program itself, the program text is
is still machine independent, but then
when it runs, it's automatically
recompiled into machine code?
Yeah, that's essentially the case. It's
And that's It is a very important
distinction between uh Java and what
we're doing here.
When When you write your program and
compile it, it gets compiled to this set
of machine instructions, the MI. And
then we take care of actually running
each of those instructions with a bunch
of microcode that sits underneath that.
So, when we move from processor
technology A to processor technology B,
we change what's happening as you
execute each of those. And so, you
really don't need to recompile. All of
your code is still written into that
same language, but we change the
underlying uh implementation, the
underlying machine instructions, actual
machine instructions that gets run.
So,
really what's happening is as you put
this program that you've written uh and
restore it from one technology onto
another, there is a retranslation that
happens where we re-implement under the
covers the actual implementation
of each of these MI instructions.
And so, you're not
you're not um just simulating what would
happen on this new box. There's no
simulation layer going on. There's no uh
going on. It's actually replacing the
implementation of the instruction set
that does your application with the new
instruction set that's necessary.
Okay. So, very much like a it's it's
kind of it's it's both. So, you're going
to have
you're going to have some intermediate
Mhm.
code and you're also going to do down
down to the bare metal code.
That's right. And and it doesn't have to
be done each time because it becomes
part of that implementation. Yep.
So, let's move on to to scaling.
And uh in IBM i and scaling, a lot of
you know, a lot of the the thought out
there is, you know, IBM systems
generally uh scale up versus scale out.
Um but I know that's not necessarily all
the case. Could you discuss for us just
a little bit more on the scaling
architecture? How does IBM i scale?
Both up as as well as out to to hit
those critical loads, whether that
happens to be business loads or internet
loads or or anything.
Okay.
Yeah, I'd be happy to talk about this.
And and to do it, we're going to have to
get into somewhat of a comparison of how
our system is used versus, say, Unix and
Windows.
First of all, we can scale to have a
single partition of i run in less than a
core on a power system all the way up to
32 or even 64 cores.
Um
and to be honest, that's what most of
our customers do. As they have more and
more business need, as they want to run
more and more on our platform. They tend
to just activate more processors on the
power processor system that they have
and we run bigger and bigger.
Now, let me explain why.
Our operating system with its subsystem
architecture
was intended to be a system where you
could run multiple workloads on the same
operating system use our work management
capabilities to balance which of those
workloads should get more of the
processor, more memory, more attention
and during which times of the day.
It also uses this object-based and
role-based security model to make sure
that two different workloads don't
interfere with one another.
So, our customers when they
created their initial business
application had things running in one
subsystem. But, when they wanted to add
to that web-based programming, for
example, and add a web server, they
could add that in a separate subsystem,
keep those two apart, and give enough
resources to the web server, but
continue to run their primary business
application.
Can you Can you clarify real quick what
the
Sure.
I would just just from you the the
subsystem. What is the difference
between
Is Is a subsystem an instance of IBM i
or is it a partition of processes in the
in the operating system? What is a
subsystem?
All right. A subsystem is a
virtualization technology that was
created initially in System 38.
But it is a way for a user to create a
smaller system within the larger system
that is isolated from everything else
but is managed by the operating system
itself. So,
I I'll use the example of a web server
versus say a payroll system.
I can put my payroll application in a
payroll subsystem, and I can say this
has the highest priority and should get
at least 50% of the memory at all times.
Then I can create another subsystem
within that partition and say, "Here's
where my web server is going to run."
Okay, it has lower priority, but it
needs to be able to respond very
quickly. And I configure information
about each of those. Now, notice it is
not a separate partition. It's running
with the same image of IBM i managing
it. And those attributes that control
how important or how much memory a
particular application, a particular
subsystem is, they're across the single
partition.
So, we created the concept because we
knew that people might want payroll to
react differently than their web server,
even though at the time web servers
didn't even exist, or whatever other
kind of application they might want to
run. We knew that customers would like
to be able to manage all of that
together as one system.
Now, over time as the industry grew up,
what we find is that, for example, a
Windows shop will have their business
application running on one system, one
physical system. And when they would
want to do a web server, they would buy
another system and put that two boxes
next to each other on a network, and
that's how they would grow up. So, they
ended up in those situations with many,
many physical systems. And when they
wanted to start doing database
applications and trying to take
advantage of the fact that they had
multiple boxes out there, they wanted to
scale out a database. Our customers
didn't have that situation. They have
one box that's running most of their
stuff. And they want to make sure that
we can scale up, but they don't really
care about adding a separate box because
they want all those workloads to be
running on that same system. So,
we typically don't talk about scaling
out very much on IBM i because our
customer set wants to be able to manage
things all within their one box. Now,
over time, we of course created
partitioning as well. When two
businesses merged and they were both
using the AS/400 or the IBM i,
they would often create a partition for
one and a partition for the other, and
then over time, those two things existed
as if they were two separate boxes. But,
by and large, most of our customers use
the subsystem model to provide the kind
of isolation that you can get that you
can count on from a partition, but also,
if you want to not have them quite so
isolated, have them be managed by the
entire system, the operating system, the
one partition.
So, really, there's
if you think about IBM i provides, just
like you said, a a virtualization within
the operating system itself. For
And again, coming from a
myself from a Unix background, you know,
those are those set of processes against
which you can put certain workload and
goal metrics.
That's right. That's right.
Well, let's move on to language support.
You know, I think maybe you can talk a
little bit about the traditional
language support in in programming
within IBM i, but then maybe move into
you know, how is programming on i
different than programming on Windows or
or Apple, any flavor of Unix there are.
So,
again, historically,
um our
customer base was interested in buying
applications.
A dentist office or a or a small bank
didn't want to have to be writing their
own applications. So, it was very key to
us that we had thousands and still have
thousands of independent software
vendors who would write software for our
platform. And we found that a lot of
them could make a very good living
because we created a programming
environment initially with a a set of
languages that were very oriented
towards doing business operations. The
most common languages
uh in the early '90s, late '80s on our
platform were two languages, one of
which
people would have heard about, COBOL.
Everybody knew COBOL in those days. And
then there was another language called
RPG. And those were very tied to our
architecture. Um COBOL, of course, was a
standard, but there were very easy uh
extensions to it that could use our
object-based and our our database model
and so on.
And many programs got written in those
languages, and they still continue to
exist. And because of the MI and our
technology independent machine
interface, those things can move forward
out without even being re- recompiled.
We were very successful with those, but
of course, there were other languages
that were being developed that other
people were learning, and they have
their own advantages as well.
So, we
very quickly added support for C, C++,
and then we really got into Java at the
same time as IBM got committed to Java
back in the '90s. So,
in addition to those initial languages
that were written, you can write in
standard C, standard C++, or standard
Java and run that on top of IBM i as
well.
Now, can it be different running on IBM
i? It certainly can. If you want to
write a Java program or a C program that
specifically takes advantage of some of
the database operations that aren't
available in SQL, you can do that. Or
you can use those languages in a pure
environment, use pure SQL to access the
database, and you are will be able to
run that same program on another
platform.
Similarly, if you wanted to take
advantage of the fact that you know that
on this platform there is a role-based
security model and an object-based
security model, you could build your
application, and many of our customers
have done that, in Java and C and C++,
accessing specific APIs to the IBM i
platform that make their
application aware of those technologies
and therefore take advantage of them. On
the other hand, if you don't want to,
you don't have to do that. So, in fact,
over time, many of our customers who
used to write only in COBOL or RPG have
actually added things like C and C++ to
their repertoire, and then how
integrated they are with the operating
system really depends on whether they
want to implement the same pieces of
software on other platforms or whether
they're just going to use them on IBM i,
in which case they tend to take
advantage of what we're doing.
These days, we have an Eclipse-based
development tool set that can do
programming or can allow you to do
programming much like you do on any
other platform because the tools are all
based on the open source Eclipse
framework.
Okay? And so, you can write your Java,
your C, your C++, or PHP, which I'll
talk about in a minute. You can write
those things using that Eclipse space
tool set, but then the target for those
those programs, those applications, can
be your IBM i. So,
I think that by and large most people
who ever heard of AS/400 thought that we
were proprietary, indifferent, and old
because we only had these
old languages that other people don't
know about. But the misconception there
is that you have to write in those
languages. And no, you don't. You can
write in these other ones.
There's a few other languages that i
supports. Smalltalk, Python,
and I think you had mentioned something
about PHP.
Mhm.
Yep.
So, all of those are supported. PHP is
the one that our customers
were really, really asking for.
And we
got into business with the Zend
Corporation. They're the folks who
the people who work for Zend are the
people who invented PHP in the first
place, and they're out there in the open
source community distributing PHP and
add-on products.
We started working with them, I think
it's been 5 years ago now, because
on our platform, we actually have what's
called PACE. It's an environment that
allows us to run
AIX programs directly on our within IBM
i. Because we have the same underlying
power architecture, we're able to put an
environment there that can take an AIX
binary and just run it straight without
having to do any interpretation or
translation or anything. Well,
PHP, the Zend Corporation had a version
of their their PHP support that could
run directly on AIX. And we said, "You
know what? Our customers have been
asking for PHP so that they could
implement web programs. And our
customers wanted to be able to do web
programming in addition to doing it in
Java, also doing it in PHP. So, we went
out and worked with Zend to get the
version of their
PHP stack that would run on a Unix.
There was a version of it that would run
on an AIX, and then we were able to
integrate that directly into IBM i.
It's been extremely successful. Now,
there's other languages that you
mentioned, they're they're available on
the platform, but they don't have a lot
of people writing in them. Nevertheless,
the people who are using them, of
course, get that same advantage of
moving from release to release without
recompiling unless they want to take
advantage of new technology.
Um but it's the PHP that's been really
taking off.
One of the other
I'm I'm not going to call it a language,
but one of the other technologies, one
of the other stacks that I've read is on
IBM i is MySQL.
Mhm.
But DB2 is integrated. Do you Is it Is
that a separate install? Can you tell me
a little bit about that MySQL
integration?
Sure.
So, MySQL
uh a couple years back created the
ability to have a separate backing
store. It essentially allowed the
allowed you to think about MySQL as a
database language, not a language plus a
backing store.
Now, most MySQL implementations assumed
that MySQL was, in fact, both the
language and the database behind it.
But,
they didn't need to think of it that
way. They could just write their their
database operations in the MySQL
language, and really didn't need to know
what was under the covers. So, when
MySQL allowed this essentially layering
approach, we created a plug-in
underneath MySQL that would actually
store data when it was operated upon by
MySQL in our DB2 for I.
So,
you can and our customers are using
this, you can access the DB2 information
on I using the MySQL language.
And so this has allowed us to pull in a
lot
of open source applications that were
written with a MySQL database storage um
and with our storage engine plugged in
under the covers,
customers can store that data from an
open source application in their DB2 for
I.
So, they can protect it and manage it
the same way that they would they do all
their others.
Plus, it's allowed us the ability to
have data that's been sitting there for
decades be accessed now by MySQL
operations.
We are not um
replacing MySQL
on our platform with DB2 and we are not
replacing DB2 with MySQL. We're treating
MySQL as another essentially programming
interface to get at the same level of
DB2. As I said before, DB2 can't even be
separated from I. So, the real uh value
that MySQL has is essentially as a
programming interface that other people
are aware of and more aware of in the
web community than other places, but
that they're aware of that can get at
that same level of data.
So, when I create a in MySQL schema and
a table in that schema, that is
available via DB2 for I.
That's right. It gets stored in DB2 for
I. That all that information's in DB2
for I and if you wanted to use
SQL or even our old programming
interfaces for our old way of doing
database to get at that data, it's all
stored in DB2 for I.
Now, it's both the syntax and the wire
pro- protocol for MySQL, which is can
expose out to all these common libraries
and and and and other programs.
That's It's very well put. It's exactly
true. It's that
It's that set of protocols and
interfaces into a database. Um
you know, sort of like JDBC, right? JDBC
is the extension to Java or the the part
of Java that allows you to do access of
database
data. Here we treat MySQL very
similarly, right? All the protocols that
are associated with MySQL still are
those protocols, but now when you
actually get to where is the data
stored, we have this extra storage
engine that we use just to put it in
DB2.
Okay, fascinating.
That's actually I I I I could see that
being uh
being quite useful. You know, MySQL
uh you know, front end and then uh back
end query through DB2.
Yep. And And those two things put
together, uh we have a we have a set of
our customers, they call themselves the
YIPs, the young I professionals.
Um
people who are in their, you know, 20s
and 30s who are using this platform. A
lot of them grew up and were educated
using things like PHP and MySQL. And so,
they can naturally put their stuff on
the platform, but they've also gone out
and
found lots of open source applications,
put them on the platform so that they
can get, you know, readily implemented,
for example, bulletin boards for their
companies and so on. They're all being
running on I, but using PHP and MySQL
because that's what the open source
application does. And so, that's
extended the number of applications that
our customers have available to them
many times because of the capabilities
we have with this set of open source
technologies.
Talk to me about the road map. Going
into this year, 2011, and into the next
year and and beyond, what do you have
planned for IBM i?
All right. Well,
that's a it's a great question
takes way more time than we probably
have, but let me give you some
highlights.
Right now, our customer set has grown up
from being
a set of customers who are very isolated
from one another
um from a technology viewpoint to
companies that, like everybody else, are
more and more connected to the internet.
And so, of course, we have all the
internet capabilities as that are
expected of an operating system. But,
one of the things that these companies
have been wanting to do is to move more
and more of their business processing um
onto the net and not necessarily have
those things be on-site systems. So, I
mentioned before our ISV community. We
have many ISVs who have transformed
their business over time to not just
selling a power system into a client and
then putting their application on it,
but also offering versions of their
software that can run as a service over
the internet.
So, we have several good examples of
ISVs like this, for example, who are
running
tens, 20s, hundreds of institutions all
within one power system running IBM i
over the network. This
software-as-a-service kind of thing has
become a pretty common way for our
clients to do their business. Well,
there's one more step that they want to
be able to take, which is to essentially
do that in a cloud environment, be able
to
easily deploy a new business, to be able
to offer their services across across
the network.
And there are some underlying
technologies that we need to make happen
within the operating system in order for
us to do that. So, there'll be a lot of
cloud-based technologies coming out
related to IBM i between now and 3 4
years from now.
Part of my job as a strategist, as an
architect, is to look out and see when
are our customers really going to be
able to consume that. And I imagine that
there'll be a great adoption of that
over the course of the next few years
because it ends up being a a way to
reliably give the customers the end user
customers the same kind of simple
application they have before, but
consolidating the management of that
into locations such as our ISV's
locations. So, that's one thing.
The other thing that I would say on our
road map is that we've recently
introduced some new DB2 technology
that's common now across all of the
DB2's related to XML support within a
database so that you can do operations
on a database uh object that are that's
actually stored in XML and you can do
that natively without having to,
deconstruct the XML and store it all in
columns and reconstruct it when you need
to reconstruct it. That is getting
significant new work done to it by all
of the databases in the industry, in
particular the DB2's. And so, we're
working with the rest of the DB2
architects to make sure that we extend
that because so much of what is going on
in the industry today is exchanging data
via the internet using XML as a way to,
of course, describe that data. And so,
there will be more that's going on there
than ever before.
Any of our listeners want to know and
learn more,
uh specifically how might they get
involved or learn more about the
development, where can they go?
Okay, well, the first place to go if you
specifically want to hear from me is I I
write a blog. Um it's from the IBM
systems magazine blog, so or website.
So, mine is
in particular is at
ibmsystemsmag.blogs.com.
And my
my blog is called you and I, so you
underscore and underscore I. So, you can
look for me there and you can learn
more. I write a blog
where I publish about once every week or
two that talks about strategy, that
talks about architecture, sometimes
specific to I or sometimes just in
general. I also talk about upcoming road
maps and things like that.
And then if you want to find information
about IBM i itself, uh you probably want
to start at ibm.com and look at the
power systems information there. We have
an entire page that's dedicated to I.
It has some really good papers connected
to it. This little bit that we talked
about about why you would use IBM i. I
have a presentation that's out there
that people can go get. Um there we link
to information that that was done as a
study to show the low total cost of
ownership for our platform. That's all
out there as well as links into our
basic information about IBM i.
And then
there is actually some YouTube
information out there. I talked about
this YI presentation.
Um somebody in our user group captured
me doing a webcast of this YI and it's
out there available on uh YouTube as
well. Um so, people can find information
primarily those ways.
Okay, great. Well, we'll we'll make sure
to provide those links.
You bet. If an application developer
wants to play around and create an
application on our platform. There
actually is a method not to download it
the capability onto your PC, but
actually access it over the internet.
There is a program called the virtual
loaner program, which
allows a a partner. And really to be a
partner at IBM, um all you have to do is
sign up and say I I want to write an
application. Okay. So, if you're a
partner at IBM,
you can reserve time on what they call
these virtual loaners. And really it's
just a partition that looks like an IBM
i system, and you can play around and
create things and do your programming
and you know, put those programs onto
the platform and so on. Now, typically
when people are doing this, they're
already partners and they have the
Rational tool set and so on. But, if
somebody wanted to play with that kind
of thing, they could download a version
of the the Rational developer tool set
for power, um
in a trial basis. They could sign up and
get a virtual loaner and and do some
programming and and mess with it that
way. But, because we're an entirely
different architecture than the x86
processors that most people are running
around with in their PCs, uh there's no
real way to develop it and then run it
on your PC. Uh instead, you need to have
access to something and that's kind of
what the virtual loaner program is for.
Because we and at our architectural
level to assume we control every bit of
disk that we have, it's a little
difficult for us to be like an
environment running on a PC because we
have to we would somehow have to be
told, "Here's the disk that you're
allowed to assume is your single-level
store." And that's not something we
typically um you know, need to worry
about.
Well, Steve, thank you very much. Is
there anything else that you would like
to add?
No, I really appreciate this opportunity
to uh talk to your audience. I'm always
looking to reach out. I do a a great
deal of speaking to customers because in
my job, trying to find out
what is going to happen in 5 years from
now really involves listening to what
our clients dealing with today that they
are going to need solved in that time
frame. And so it's exciting to be able
to have audience to tell this to so that
I might hear from other people about the
kinds of issues that they're seeing and
how operating systems can help them in
the future. Thank you very much.
Thanks for listening to Software
Engineering Radio. SE Radio is an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Europe. If you want more
information about the podcast and the
other episodes, visit our website at
SE-Radio.net.
If you want to support us, you can
donate to the SE Radio team via the
website or you can advertise for SE
Radio for example by clicking on the
Digg, Reddit, Delicious, and Slashdot
buttons or by talking about us on
Twitter and Facebook. You can also
support us by joining team and
shouldering some of the work.
To contact the team, please send email
to team@se-radio.net
or if your feedback is specific to an
episode, please use the comments
facility on the website so other people
can react to your comments. This episode
of SE Radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under a Creative
Commons 2.5 license. Please see the
website for details.